<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.4.1//EN"
  "http://docbook.sourceforge.net/release/website/2.4.1/schema/dtd/website.dtd" []>

<webpage id="2005-issue01-editorial">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial</title>

<!--
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Mikhail</firstname>
        <surname>Zotov</surname>
      </author>
      <author>
        <firstname>Daniel</firstname>
        <surname>de Kok</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
-->
  </head>

  <sect1>
    <para>
      After a month of hard work the first issue of <emphasis>The Slack
      World</emphasis> is ready. This project was started by Mickhail
      Zotov and Alan Hicks to provide a high quality monthly Slackware Linux 
      newsletter that provides in-depth articles and Slackware related
      news coverage. Along the way Daniel de Kok also joined the project,
      and worked on the XML framework.
    </para>

    <para>
      We are aware of the fact that new Slackware-related
      initiatives pop up everywhere every month, and that we will have to
      prove ourselves to be a project that provides valuable information
      and continuity. We ask you, as a reader, to judge our little
      new project by the quality of the contents, and to provide
      feedback. We just got started, and would like to know how we can
      improve things
    </para>

    <para>
      This first issue contains some sections that we plan to include
      every month:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <emphasis role="bold">Editorial</emphasis>: what is a magazine
	without an editorial? The editorial will comment on new
	developments in the GNU/Linux world, or beg for new articles.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <emphasis role="bold">Slack News</emphasis>: the Slack News
	section is a monthly summary of developments related to
	Slackware Linux.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <emphasis role="bold">Slack Wisdom</emphasis>: Slack Wisdom
	is a montly section that gathers Slack wisdom from various
	newsgroups and mailinglists.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <emphasis role="bold">Slackopedia</emphasis>: The Slackopedia
	section contains an in-depth article about some Slackware-related
	subject.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      We hope that you will enjoy this first issue, have a good read!
    </para>

    <literallayout>
Your editors,

Daniel de Kok
Mickhail Zotov
    </literallayout>

  </sect1>

</webpage>
