<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.4.1//EN"
  "http://docbook.sourceforge.net/release/website/2.4.1/schema/dtd/website.dtd" []>

<webpage id="2005-issue01-editorial">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial</title>
  </head>

  <section>

    <para>
      After a month of hard work the first issue of <emphasis>The Slack
      World</emphasis> is ready. This project was started by Mickhail
      Zotov and Alan Hicks to provide a high quality monthly Slackware Linux 
      newsletter that provides in-depth articles and Slackware related
      news coverage. The project was first publicly announced on the
      alt.os.linux.slackware newsgroup:
    </para>

    <blockquote>
      <literallayout>
Newsgroups: alt.os.linux.slackware
From: Mikhail Zotov &lt;e-boogie blah@blah yandex . ru&gt;
Date: Mon, 28 Feb 2005 21:32:34 +0300
Local: Mon, Feb 28 2005 10:32 am
Subject: New project: The Slack World

Ladies and gentlemen, folks, fellow slackers,

We are going to begin a new project (tentatively and very modestly
called "The Slack World").  The main aim of the project is to fill
a few gaps that we see in covering Slackware-related information by
other resources.

The project is geared towards both Slackware veterans and novices.
Currently, we think about covering the following main topics/sections:

* Feature pieces (aka Slackopaedia), i.e., articles written by experienced
  users for experienced users and newbies and covering subjects that are
  not widely known but useful (gnupg, apache, sendmail, mysql, backup scripts,
  etc.)  This is to be a sort of mini-HOWTO section and may cover things
  included with Slackware or things not included with Slackware.

* Brief reviews of the changes in -current tree (aka Slack News).

* The most insightful and information things mentioned in AOLS or
  ##slackware or #slackware or elsewhere (aka Slack Wisdom).

* Information about new or existing third party tools developed around
  Slackware, including distributions based on Slack.

* Possibly, other topics related to Slackware and Linux in general
  (e.g., links to articles that may be of general interest).

We intend to implement the project as a monthly newsletter backed by
a no-frills website.

We would very much like to hear your opinions, ideas, suggestions.
We also invite volunteers to join the project.  Last but not least, we
would very much like to receive your articles, tips, links, etc. as soon
as the project is up and you like it. :-)

Best regards,

Alan Hicks (http://slackbook.lizella.net) and Mikhail Zotov
(http://slackfire.narod.ru) 
      </literallayout>
    </blockquote>

    <para>
      Along the way Daniel de Kok also joined the project as an author
      and editor, and worked on the XML framework. Unfortunately Alan
      Hicks had to drop the project, due to other commitments.
    </para>

    <para>
      We are aware of the fact that new Slackware-related
      initiatives pop up everywhere every month, and that we will have to
      prove ourselves to be a project that provides valuable information
      and continuity. We ask you, as a reader, to judge our little
      new project by the quality of the contents, and to provide
      feedback. We just got started, and would like to know how we can
      improve things
    </para>

    <para>
      This first issue contains some sections that we plan to include
      every month:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <emphasis role="bold">Editorial</emphasis>: what is a magazine
	without an editorial? The editorial will comment on new
	developments in the GNU/Linux world, or beg for new articles.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <emphasis role="bold">Slack News</emphasis>: the Slack News
	section is a monthly summary of developments related to
	Slackware Linux.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <emphasis role="bold">Slack Wisdom</emphasis>: Slack Wisdom
	is a montly section that gathers Slack wisdom from various
	newsgroups and mailinglists.
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <emphasis role="bold">Slackopedia</emphasis>: The Slackopedia
	section contains an in-depth article about some Slackware-related
	subject.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      We hope that you will enjoy this first issue, have a good read!
    </para>

    <literallayout>
Your editors,

Daniel de Kok
Mickhail Zotov
    </literallayout>

  </section>

</webpage>
