<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.4.1//EN"
  "http://docbook.sourceforge.net/release/website/2.4.1/schema/dtd/website.dtd" []>

<webpage id="2005-issue01-hhkb">
  <head>
    <title>Happy Hacking Keyboard Lite 2</title>
    <subtitle>UNIX keyboards done the right way</subtitle>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Daniel</firstname>
        <surname>de Kok</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </head>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      Every UNIX user who has ever touched more than 
      <ulink url="http://kate.kde.org/">Kate</ulink> or
      <ulink url="http://www.gnome.org/projects/gedit/">gedit</ulink> knows
      that standard PC keyboards are plain wrong. First, of all the ESC
      and CTRL keys are wronly placed. Besides that the average keyboard
      is like a dinasaur when you only need a few letters for navigation.
      One common technique to solve the first problem is to remap Caps
      lock to CTRL, and the backtick key to ESC. But 
      <ulink url="http://www.pfu.fujitsu.com/">PFU Limited</ulink> (a
      Fujitsu company) has made a series of keyboards designed to solve
      both problems, the 
      <ulink url="http://www.pfu.fujitsu.com/en/hhkeyboard/">Happy Hacking
      Keyboard</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
      Since I am an avid elvis/vim/nvi user I have been watching development
      around the Happy Hacking Keyboard (HHKB) for quite some time. Recently
      I purchased a HHKB Lite 2 white USB for $59.95 from
      <ulink url="http://www.linuxcentral.com">Linux Central</ulink>. I
      chose for the Lite 2 version for two reasons: the other models are
      to expensive for a student budget, and it has inverted T arrow
      keys. Both the normal and Pro versions do not have inverted T
      arrows, but I think it is certainly possible to manage to survive
      without.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Keyboard characteristics</title>

    <para>
      The keyboard arrived in a somewhat cheap looking blue box, that
      contains has a short and handy overview of the keyboard and
      keyboard settings on the back. It was only until I opened the
      box that I realized how small the keyboard actually is (quite
      cute). The footprint of the HHKB is
      <ulink url="http://www.pfu.fujitsu.com/en/hhkeyboard/leaflet/kbhiaku.html">compared</ulink>
      to other keyboards on the website, but when you actually see
      the keyboard, the cut-off seems really radical. It really cleans
      up my desk.
    </para>

    <mediaobject id="hhkb-lite2">
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata format="JPG" fileref="images/hhkb.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>Blowfish is guarding the keyboard</caption>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>
      The keyboard has some really nice features, like two upstream
      USB ports (of course, only the USB version), that are very handy
      when you carry around USB mass storage alot. Besides that there
      are some dip switches hidden behind a small plate that you
      can pop off. The table listed below gives a short overview of
      the dip switches.
    </para>

    <table>
      <title>Happy Hacking Keyboard Lite 2 dip switches</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <thead>
	  <row>
	    <entry>Dip switch</entry><entry>Description</entry>
	  </row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry>1</entry>
	    <entry>Enable/disable upstream USB ports</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>2</entry>
	    <entry>Not used</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>3</entry>
	    <entry>Delete is delete/Delete is backspace</entry>
	  </row>
	  <row>
	    <entry>4</entry>
	    <entry>Swapping of ALT and diamond keys</entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>

    <para>
      These dip switches are well-documented in the Japanese/English
      leaflet that is included in the box. At first the switches looked
      a bit easily breakable to me, but I managed to use them without
      breaking anything, and I am probably only going to set the switches
      once.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Configuring the keyboard</title>

    <para>
      Configuring the keyboard involves two steps: setting the dip switches,
      and setting up the software. I turned switch 3 to let the delete key
      act as backspace, since I use backspace quite a lot when I am editing.
    </para>

    <para>
      As I expected the software configuration turned out to be a no-brainer:
      hotplugging + kernel USB magic automatically detected the keyboard:
    </para>

    <screen>
input: USB HID v1.00 Keyboard [Chicony  PFU-65 USB Keyboard] on usb-0000:00:10.0-2.1
    </screen>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>How it feels</title>

    <para>
      Immediately after plugging in the keyboard and typing some shell
      commands it occured to me that the HHKB feels very natural in my
      hands. It feels like the keyboard is well thought-out, and that
      even normal letter keys feel better than an average keyboard. Having
      the CTRL and ESC keys at another place did not involve much of
      a relearning curve. I never used CTRL or ESC remappings, but
      automatically started to use the CTRL and ESC correctly on the
      HHKB.
    </para>

    <para>
      The HHKB Lite 2 keys use a membrane switch that is depressed by a
      rubber cap. This gives a minor click, but not as much as old
      IBM keyboards. I personally severy dislike keyboards without a
      click, because it gives good feedback when I type. My fingers
      have got used to that over years. The click on this keyboard
      is just about right. The 
      <ulink url="http://www.pfu.fujitsu.com/en/hhkeyboard/leaflet/keyspec.html">key pressure</ulink> 
      of the Lite 2 keyboard is about 55g, which feels pretty normal.
    </para>

    <para>
      My primary critique about the HHKB is that the backtick key
      is at an awkward place. Is use it quite a lot when I am
      editing shell scripts. This can be worked around by remapping
      the diamond key.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Conclusion</title>
    
    <para>
      Although keyboards are a matter of personal preference, I wholeheartedly
      recommend the Happy Hacking Keyboard Lite 2 to anyone who uses
      Slackware Linux in a UNIXy way. If you are not used to work
      wth UNIX editors like vi, it may be a bit hard to get used
      to the HHKB, since some keys are not directly available
      (like the function keys). But if you are, this keyboard just
      feels perfect, with everything you need available without much
      hand movement. If you are still using a lot of garbage keys
      this is a good opportunity to learn to het rid of them.
    </para>

    <para>
      After using the HHKB for a short while you will see how
      used you get to it when you use another keyboard. You will be
      hitting the Caps lock key all the time. But there really is
      no excuse not to cary a USB HHKB with you with its current
      size. I would love to get my hands on a normal or Pro version
      of the keyboard, but with the price tags of the other versions,
      I guess nobody has a spare for me ;).
    </para>
  </section>

</webpage>
