<?xml version="1.0"?>

<!DOCTYPE webpage PUBLIC "-//Norman Walsh//DTD Website V2.4.1//EN"
  "http://docbook.sourceforge.net/release/website/2.4.1/schema/dtd/website.dtd" []>

<webpage id="2005-issue01-slacknews">
  <head>
    <title>SlackNews</title>

    <editor>
      <firstname>Daniel</firstname>
      <surname>de Kok</surname>
    </editor>
  </head>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      This monthly section gives a brief overview of Slackware-related
      news.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>GNOME dropped from Slackware-Current</title>

    <para>
      After a long period of consideration GNOME is dropped in
      Slackware-Current. From the
      <ulink url="http://www.slackware.com/changelog/current.php?cpu=i386">ChangeLog</ulink>:
    </para>

    <blockquote>
      <literallayout>
gnome/*: Removed from -current, and turned over to community support and
   distribution. I'm not going to rehash all the reasons behind this, but it's
   been under consideration for more than four years.
      </literallayout>
    </blockquote>

    <para>
      This should come as no big surprise, since this has been announced
      pretty long ago. A widely circulated 
      <ulink url="http://www.dropline.net/forums/viewtopic.php?t=3430">e-mail</ulink> 
      from Patrick Volkerding that was originally posted on the Dropline
      GNOME forums already indicated that the removal of GNOME was under
      consideration:
    </para>

    <blockquote>
      <literallayout>
Anyway, suffice to say the jury is still out. Since GNOME 1.4 I've felt
that GNOME is going in a direction that doesn't fit well with Slackware's
goals, and for at least as long I've considered removing it completely and
taking whatever flames I get for that decision. Right now, I think
removing it would be the best thing for Slackware as it's become a
maintainance nightmare (unlike nearly every other ./configure'ed source,
GNOME doesn't build into packages easily with DESTDIR).

Not what you wanted to hear, I'm sure, but I do believe it would be best
to let Dropline produce Slackware's GNOME and quit wasting my own time
with it. Probably 1/3 of developement time here is used maintaining
GNOME, and *most* of the bug reports I get have something to do with GNOME
(and aren't bugs I caused, or can fix). KDE, on the other hand, tends to
build using the existing build scripts with no changes at all. I can
start the build and come back to finished packages in a few hours. A
GNOME update usually takes at least a week of manual labor, and another
week of cleaning up broken things. It's been a long time (like I said,
around GNOME 1.4), since I've felt the effort was worth the return. 
      </literallayout>
    </blockquote>

    <para>
      This does not mean that GNOME users are left out in the cold.
      Both the <ulink url="http://gsb.sourceforge.net/">GNOME.SlackBuild</ulink>
      and the <ulink url="http://gware.sourceforge.net/">GWARE</ulink>
      projects provide GNOME 2.10 for Slackware Linux. Both projects
      that provide a non-intrusive version of GNOME, which means that
      replacement of official Slackware Linux packages is avoided. The
      better known <ulink url="http://www.dropline.net/gnome/">Dropline
      GNOME</ulink> project also provides GNOME 2.10 packages for Slackware
      Linux. But Dropline is highly intrusive, and amongst others add PAM
      and their own X.org builds. Time will tell what (if any) will become 
      the defacto GNOME for Slackware Linux.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>KDE in Slackware-Current upgraded to 3.4.0</title>

    <para>
      As usual, new KDE packages are available after the new release
      of KDE. New features in KDE 3.4 include:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A text to speech system, with support built into Konqueror,
          Kate, KPDF and KSayIt. Besides that text to speech synthesis
          is integrated with the desktop.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          KPDF now has support for copying images and text from PDF
          files.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support for various groupware servers, including eGroupware,
          Groupwise, Kolab, OpenGroupware.org and SLOX, in Kontact.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support for Novel Groupwise and Lotus Sametime in Kopete.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Improved standards support in the Konqueror web browser.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Many other features are listed in the 
      <ulink url="http://www.kde.org/announcements/announce-3.4.php">release
      notes</ulink>. Proponents of new Linux desktop technologies might
      want to add that KDE now has DBUS/HAL support for keeping dynamic
      device icons in <filename>media:/</filename>. It should be noted
      that HAL is not included in Slackware Linux. At the moment HAL is
      limited to Linux kernel 2.6, and pretty experimental. 
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Dead trees version of the not-so-unofficial Slack Book available</title>

    <para>
      Many Slackware Linux fans were probably be relieved to hear that
      the <ulink url="http://www.slackbook.org/">The Unofficial Revised
      Slackware Book Project</ulink> is now
      <ulink url="http://store.slackware.com/cgi-bin/store/slackbook">available</ulink>
      through the <ulink url="http://store.slackware.com/">Slackware Store</ulink>.
      Now we can now finally go out, and give our newbie friends a
      good introductory work to Slackware Linux. Thanks go out to
      Alan Hicks and his
      <ulink url="http://www.slackbook.org/contributors.html">team</ulink>
      for their great work!
    </para>
  </section>

</webpage>
